almost 30 years ago
I had the opportunity to visit my older
cousin who was an Episcopalian priest of
the Ango anglo-catholic mode
in Philadelphia
and
this cousin of mine is very refined and
cultured he's a real student of the Fine
Arts and on that occasion he took me
downtown to Wanamaker's department store
now the purpose of that visit was not to
make purchases but because wanamakers
was featuring a display of a famous
painting by Rembrandt Von Ron
and the name of the painting is
Aristotle
contemplating the bust of Homer
and so my highly refined cousin said to
me as we approached the store he said to
me he said boy you're going to get
an expansion of your understanding of
beauty today he said cousin he said
we're going to get to see that world
famous painting Aristotle contemplating
the home of Buster
obviously I haven't forgotten that a
slip of the tongue but today we're going
to contemplate a bus but it's not the
bust of Homer it's the bust of Plato
because I've sort of wanted to have
Plato come and visit us as we discuss
some of his thinking I was able to
secure this bust recently in a trip to
Italy in the coastal town of Amalfi and
I also purchased a bust of Alexander the
Great
because I thought I shouldn't come home
with just one because they tell me the
two heads are better than one but in any
case today we're going to be talking
about my friend Plato
who along with his most famous student
Aristotle are considered the real twin
Giants of Western philosophy in fact one
historian of philosophy made the
observation that all subsequent work in
the field of Philosophy by Future
generations and future philosophers is
nothing more than footnotes added to the
thinking of Plato and Aristotle so
prodigious were these men in their own
day now we also notice that I have a
chair with me today and it's not because
I'm going to be lazy and sit down and
give you a far side chat but there's a
method to my madness as I hope we will
see in a few moments the reason for this
chair is really not for me to sit in but
to use as a prop to illustrate one of
the most important principles of Plato's
philosophy but you're going to have to
wait for that for a couple of moments
Plato
was born in the year 427 BC and you'll
recall that's basically 28 years before
The Death of Socrates which means that
Plato was 28 the year that Socrates died
Plato wasn't his real name Plato was his
nickname
and there was a nickname given to him by
his coach when he was a young gymnast
and wrestler who wrestled in the games
that were the precursors of what we now
call the Olympic Games but because of
his powerful built build
he was called Plato which means broad
shoulders
and that became His Name by which we
know him today
his personal family background was of
high nobility his mother
was a direct descendant of Solon the
great political thinker of ancient
Athens and his father was a descendant
of one of the recent Kings of Athens so
there was great royalty and nobility in
the blood of Plato who was born into an
aristocratic family
now
he's known for being the founder of a
very important School in Athens that is
called the academy
and the name Academy is drawn from the
name of the person
who presumably had owned a piece of
property in the Northwest Quadrant right
outside the city of Athens a man by the
name of akademus
and he had some olive Groves in this
area and donated a parcel of this land
so that Plato could start his school and
he honored
academies by calling his school the
academy and it was situated in the midst
of this Grove of olive trees and that's
where we get the expression The Groves
of Academia that we still use to define
the academic world in which we live
today now over the entrance to the
school
or the academy
Plato had a fixed on an arch over the
door these words
let none but geometers enter here
sort of like Dante's sign over the door
to Hades despair of Hope or abandon hope
all ye who enter here Plato sign read
let none but geometers enter here now
wait a minute we think of Plato
as the great philosopher not the great
mathematician why would he call his
school a school of geometry
well in the first instance Plato's
School covered the whole scope of
intellectual inquiry from uh
political Theory to ethics to The
Sciences and so on
so it wasn't just the school for
mathematicians and yet he says let none
but geometers enter here
now to understand that you can't think
of it in terms of what we call Modern
geometry
the word geometry comes from the Greek
word gase or the word for Earth
and the word uh when we talk about metre
or meter we talk about that which is a
form of measurement
and so originally the science of
geometry was the science of measuring
elements of the Earth
and it was done by an examination of the
forms of measurement which we did study
in modern geometry like the triangle and
the rectangle and the square and so on
and so by means of these various shapes
or forms that we use to measure things
mathematically we call the science
geometry but Plato Went A Step Beyond
this by saying that the Universe in
which we live is not simply measured by
forms
but rather the universe is
that reality is
mathematical forms or ideas at that
point we see something of the influence
of the earlier pythagoreans who had a
virtually mystical view of numbers but
that's another story for another
occasion
a Plato's great contribution to the
history of philosophy is in the
development of what is called his theory
of ideas
his theory of ideas or it's sometimes
called his theory of forms
his theory of forms
now
Plato
is what we call
an idealist or
we could say that Plato
more accurately
is a realist
and you say wait a minute are you
talking out of both sides of your mouth
how can he be both an idealist and a
realist well let's think about that for
a second when we use the term
idealist
over against the term realist what do we
usually have in mind we think of an
idealist as somebody who's kind of
pollyannish who lives in a make-believe
world of ideals who never comes to grip
with the Grim and harsh realities of the
actual World in which we live in and a
realist is the one who draws his Heroes
warts and all he doesn't try to give us
a a phantom
image of Ideal Perfection so for us a
realist stands in stark contrast to an
idealist
but when we call Plato an idealist
and a realist we are using those terms
in a significantly different way and see
if I can explain that
Plato said that the Ultimate Reality the
ultimate realities I should say plural
are ideas
the truth is ultimately formal not
Material
that the ideas that we have in our minds
of various things
are a recall of ideas that actually
exist
in a spiritual realm what we would call
a super temporal realm a realm above and
beyond this world of physical things
that we perceive every day
now let me see in order to illustrate
that the use of my prop that I brought
here today
I'm going to ask for some help from our
audience here to see if we can learn
something about Plato's theory of ideas
I have my friend Roger my super student
who sits here in the front row and Roger
never ceases to amaze me with his
prodigious grasp of these difficult calm
and complex ideas I'm not going to
embarrass the adults by asking them
questions that they'll stumble over
instead I I will go to Roger because I
know he'll be able to answer this
question the question I have for you
Roger it's a very difficult question
you're going to have to think hard I
have this object in front of me what is
it
a chair all right Roger thank you you
got it right on the button he said
that's a chair
now here's the question
how do you know it's a chair
how do you know it's a chair Roger
you just grew up learning that that was
a chair right you never saw that chair
before today what do you mean you grew
up learning that that was a cheer
but you came in here never saw that
chair before in your life and then as
soon as I asked you what I want you what
did you say no hesitation it's a chair
how did you recognize it as a chair
it has four legs
all right but you know horses have four
legs aren't they Roger uh we're gonna do
this in the socratic dialogue here
horses have four legs but you don't call
them chairs do you
all right so there must be something
else besides this having four legs that
made you identified as a chair
what else
you can sit on it but of course you
can't sit on a horse can you Roger
huh
do you have anything at home that's
that's kind of long has three like three
sections to it that has legs four legs
and
you can sit on it
call it a sofa
but you know the difference between a
sofa and a chair don't you
yes sir
well I could we could pursue this a
little bit further because have you ever
seen chairs that don't look exactly like
this Roger
yes sir you've seen uh chairs that are
upholstered and real comfortable right
you've seen
wooden chairs and
soft chairs and hard chairs and all
different kinds of chairs in fact every
one of us has probably seen literally
thousands of different kinds of chairs
right
different shapes different sizes
different material
And yet when we see these thousands of
different particular objects
we can look at them and in spite of the
differences that are displayed among
them we still have this uncanny ability
to put all of these particulars all of
these specific examples into the same
category called
chair
all right
and so Plato would scratch his head and
say well how can we do that how is it
that we have this ability as thinking
creatures to recognize all these vastly
different objects by the same common
Universal term called a chair
or I look out here in the audience and I
see
people
I see young people and old people male
people and female people thin people and
heavy people don't I blue eyes and brown
eyes
they're every person in this room has
their unique
identification
and yet I can look at all of these
particular examples of people
and somehow extrapolate from these
different individuals
a class that we call human beings or
people or mankind
Plato was once challenged to give a
succinct definition
for what it means to be human
and he said that a human a man or a
human
is a featherless biped
that is a two-footed creature without
feathers
until one of his students through a
pluck chicken over the wall of the
academy with a sign around its neck that
said Plato's man it was a featherless
biped
but in any case what Plato was saying
when he when he contemplated all of this
is
how is it that we have this ability to
recognize so many particular objects
by this Universal category
of chair-ness
we have an idea in our mind of chairness
we have an idea in our mind of closeness
we have an idea in our minds of
humanness
of treeness of street-ness
and so whenever we see a particular
Street or a particular tree or a
particular man such as Plato
we can recognize them
insofar as they approximate the idea
of humanness treeness cheerness
straightness or whatever it is
now Plato says the reason that is is
that in this spiritual Realm
there is the eternal perfect idea of
tree
there is the perfect
Eternal idea of chair
Eternal idea of human
and everything that we meet in this
world
is simply
a copy
of the archetypal idea or ideal now what
he's saying is is that these ideas
independently exist apart from us
they have real being
now do you see what Plato's getting at
here is the old problem that was left
unresolved between Parmenides and
heraclitus
how can we account
for both being
and becoming
this is the world the world that we see
and perceive with our senses for Plato
is the world of becoming
and the only way we can have any
knowledge of this realm is because above
this realm of becoming is the realm of
being
where the Eternal ideas of things
actually exists now let me just pause
for a minute and say do you see how he's
called an idealist he's called an
idealist because he says that ultimate
truth is found in these Eternal ideas
and it is the formal truth
that it's the highest truth
but the ideas for Plato are not merely
constructs of the human mind
they are not just human ways of thinking
about things but these ideas really are
they have ontological status they have
real being
and in that sense he's called a realist
Because he believes
that the ideas are not just imaginary
but they are real now do you see how he
can be both a realist and an idealist in
the sense in which I'm using those terms
at the same
time
now
one of the important aspects of this
kind of thinking that has had a profound
effect on every one of you
and of your lives down to this very day
you live in a world you grow up in an
environment where you even now struggle
with the idea
that physical things
food
drink sex
anything that is physical
sort of is infected by a shadow
of evil
even in the church we saw the church in
the Middle Ages in the monastic movement
and so on try to deny all things
physical
things of bodily appetites like hunger
and drink and that these participation
in eating and in Sex and in in drinking
were necessary of course for human
survival and for the propagation of the
species but they were necessary evils
where does that guy deer come from it
doesn't come from the Old Testament
where when God creates a physical world
what's his judgment on it
it's good
it can be misused and there are evil
uses of good things but there's no
inherent wickedness to the physical as
far as the Bible is concerned
but remember in Plato schema you have
two worlds the ideal world the Eternal
world of ideas and then this world
where you have the particulars now these
particular objects that we recognize as
chairs
he calls receptacles
a receptacle is something that receives
and contains something
and for Plato the receptacle
is the particular object
that
copies to some degree
the pure idea
but all receptacles that is all physical
things you me this chair the tree the
street anything that is physical
is a receptacle and anything that is
receptacle is according to Plato an
imperfect copy
of the spiritual ideal
so that by its necessary state of
existence anything physical is imperfect
now when he says imperfect he means
metaphysically imperfect but it's a
short step from metaphysical
imperfection to moral imperfection
so that anything that is imperfect
Lacks
pure goodness
and from that we get a whole history of
philosophies that reject and deny
the goodness of the created world
for example in the Christian faith as we
will see in our next lecture We Believe
in the resurrection of the body that's
part of our faith
the Redemption of the Body for Plato
Redemption comes when we get rid of the
body
it's Redemption from the body
when you're only really redeemed when
you live in a pure state of spirit and
of idea
now this is all kinds of implications
for Plato's theory of knowledge which
we'll look at in our next session